I'm not the same person
that I was before the shooting.
THE ACTORS
AND THE JOURNALIST
OF IT ALL
Autumn in the country
can be really muggy.
If I'm so bad, then how come
I take home the money?
He's a sick man.
- Have you said different things?
- I understand the question.
I do connect
with one of the monkeys.
Why are you so dressed up today?
- "Bryggeren"?
- No, I wasn't in that either.
Can I ask you something?
I decided to wear black.
It makes you look thinner.
- "Matador"?
- No. Before my time.
- I wore it at the premiere.
- I can't remember that.
Anyone can call himself an actor
if he earns a million a year.
Auteur, director, Trier...
the words are connected.
Lars von Trier has joie de vivre.
He's a vibrant and playful man.
In this movie, he plays
with the medium once again.
It's called "Automavision."
Pre-fabricated images.
A computer has planned it all.
Trier has let the machine decide.
Utterly weird.
When I first heard about it
I didn't understand a damned thing.
It was a constant source of fun
because it's so stupid.
You have lots of actors,
and then the camera
opts to film a kitchen roll.
I thought, "What the hell
is he up to this time?"
There had to be some obstructions.
6 minutes' worth of kitchen roll
footage which will never be used.
Here's a new film.
It may look strange to you,
but hang in there. There's
something for everyone, I promise.
When does art become art?
When does it speak to the heart,
when does it speak to the mind?
These questions are...
Those are questions you have to ask
when you see a new Trier movie.
He's just made the comedy
"The Boss of It AII."
We've talked to the actors about art.
Comedy is fun. This is serious.
What was it like for you
to expose yourself so much
while also working with your
boyfriend, Casper Christensen?
Could you cope,
with him on the sideline?
Yes.
I thought it was great to see
how Casper came alive as an actor
in a more classical sense.
Are you done now?
- Iben, your part is a major one.
- Yes. It is.
It's required
a lot of preparation work.
Shut up. We'll be
more upset if you don't tell us.
- And clearly a difficult one.
- Yes, and you could say...
She's ambitious, you know.
She really wants to reach the top.
There'll be no banging
until you've had a good licking.
Trier has based your character
on your own life.
What's it like,
playing yourself in a movie?
Playing myself in a movie?
We use different sides of ourselves,
of course, but I'm not playing me.
- Overall, you mean?
- Yes, for example.
Well...
- He resembles you, doesn't he?
- According to Trier, he does.
But I'm not so sure.
He says you're quite soft
and inconsistent.
Do you see yourself that way?
There's nothing wrong
with being soft, but inconsistent...
Come on.
Up you go. That's it.
Big hug.
You helped Casper with his lines
and coached him, I guess.
- Did that help your own character?
- No, I have to say...
- Can I...?
- Hold on. Let me finish.
- Casper had to start from scratch.
- No, I didn't.
Yes, you did. Completely.
Mentally speaking, you're like
a newborn baby in this context.
Sofie, one of your big scenes
is in the zoo, at the monkey cage.
What do you do as an actor
to use the environment
and draw on that for your part?
I didn't have any dialogue
with them, you know.
Did you feel any connection
with the monkey?
It's embarrassing, but I can't
remember what they are. Baboons?
Jens Albinus, you've played with
Trier before. How was it this time?
I don't understand the question.
- You know him.
- I've never played with him.
No one has told me
you would ask about that.
What I meant was, you've
been in a Trier movie before.
Oh, yes. Right...
But it was different
this time around.
- It was completely different.
- In what way?
Let me just say that it has to do
with certain members of the cast.
My base of experience
is enormous, as you know.
I've created my own method...
the Gantzler Method as I call it...
so that when I get a new part
I know exactly how to approach it.
And this guy, Ravn,
was no exception.
He's called Ravn ("raven").
It's a bird. There's your opening.
Ravn, Ravn, Ravn...
- You haven't felt insecure?
- Not that much.
I don't run around like an idiot
with all your touchy-feely crap...
- Who do you think you are?
- I tell it like it is.
You don't know anything.
You just come stomping in...
"I'll go in and impress
Lars von Trier..."
- Well, it works.
- No, it doesn't! You just sit there.
If it hadn't been for me
you would have looked like a dork.
You're this close, you know.
Can you be more specific?
What is it you want to say?
You have to watch what you say.
Peter, you're being very candid
about the Gantzler Method.
Was it a technical handle
that you and Trier talked about
developing along the way?
Let me put it this way.
I'm absolutely certain that Lars
was aware that I had
this very special technique.
We didn't discuss it that much.
Personally, I don't like
having people poke around
in my techniques.
But I've heard
through other people
that Lars has talked about me
in very positive terms...
not just as an individual,
but also as an actor.
He described the method
as being very valuable.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
It's fine if you want to walk
through life with the hollow idea
that you have any talent at all.
I'm not listening to this shit.
I'd like to get out!
Fear is poetry, poetry is fear.
The two are closely linked
in the world of art,
in the world of Trier.
Many actors use fear
as a driving force.
So you could ask,
"Is fear a driving force?"
Louise, were you afraid
during the filming?
Yes, she was. A bit.
- What?
- Why do you say that?
As an actor, you're always afraid
of not being good enough.
And not being loved.
That's why we do it, you know.
- Were you afraid as well?
- Yes.
Yes. She was.
You joke a lot. Sometimes
I don't know exactly what to think.
I can't respond when I don't
know if it was a joke or not.
Do you have any experience
in working with monkeys?
Yes, I have.
I've tried it before.
Do you make any demands
in that sort of situation:
"This time I don't want
to touch the monkey"?
No. Did I want different animals
this time, you mean?
Yes, or contact with the monkeys,
quite simply.
- Sorry?
- That you didn't want that.
No, I can't say that. There's
a reason why he chose monkeys.
If that's what's best for the scene,
then I'm ready to do it.
The whole acting business
is incredibly hollow.
It's not something you can learn.
You either have it, or you don't.
I think Iben's got it.
She's really talented.
But she's getting older,
so she can't pick and choose.
Timing isn't something
you can learn in a school.
So all their National School
of Theatre crap...
running around, going
"Can you feel the sand?"
when there isn't any goddamn sand.
Who are you trying to fool?
I've been an actor for 16 years.
I've been in 15-20 films.
- I'm thinking "Walter and Carlo"?
- No, that wasn't me.
Do you even know my name?
I've got the rare ability
to influence people around me
just by thinking certain things.
Therefore, if I see an actor
who hasn't quite got it,
I can mentally transfer
direction tips to Lars,
which he can then pass on.
Usually with great success.
Peter Gantzler is
a very, very sick man.
- What do you mean by that?
- Let's not get into that.
Peter Gantzler, a sick man?
He's just an actor, isn't he?
It's a good thing that I'm
the director, and you're just an actor.
I sense a story behind your fear.
What is that story about?
It...
I'd rather not talk about it.
Don't say anything.
Gosh...
You must have been
afraid of Automavision?
We've actually invented this thing
called "Automa-action."
It's very similar.
When you pose a question,
you think you're getting the
corresponding answer, but you're not.
As an actor, does fear have to be
part of your toolbox, so to say?
No, I don't think so.
I think...
Well... the canteen food
was quite varied, don't you think?
It was... It was the highlight
of the day, you know?
Whether or not
you got any satisfaction...
foodwise.
It's about whether or not
you project. That's the thing.
If you've wasted four years,
fucking around, drinking beer,
trying to dance a certain color
in slippers... no wonder you're bitter.
When the rest of us can get by
just with high school, you know.
Which films have you been in?
There are so many.
I can't remember them all.
There's been... I've said no
to a lot of things as well.
Is it Trier you're afraid of?
In what way do you feel
that Trier is an auteur?
Ask me about something else.
When Trier calls you do you think,
"Trier... that means awards"?
- "This will get me another award"?
- Yes.
If we talk ticket sales
or ratings
or "TV Host of The Year"
in the weekly magazines...
I don't know if you want to go
there, but if you do...
then yes, we've all won awards.
Have you noticed the drastic change
in the North Zealand weather
after we shot this movie?
- What?
- I live in the northern part.
The weather in my garden
hasn't been the same since.
- What's it got to do with Gantzler?
- Well, ask him that.
Not all actors are equally
responsive, you know.
And the casting on this film...
I didn't have time to give Lars
specific instructions about
who I would like to see
in the various parts,
so his choices are a bit...
shaky in places.
But... to err is human.
But it was difficult,
especially with...
with Jens.
I've got this spot between
the second and third vertebrae
which hasn't been the same since.
And every time I hear his name
it gets worse.
God, I'm furious!
Ravn is the key character,
so it's important to me
that Jens respects the fact that
I'm the star, and follows my lead.
That was hard for him.
He clearly has no method whatsoever.
He's out of a very different,
more clownlike tradition, perhaps.
It's terribly difficult
to work with sometimes.
You're just acting scared now.
Yeah, that's right. I am.
We're just acting.
That's an actor's specialty.
- Were you in "The Idiots"?
- Yes, I was, actually.
- Have you seen it?
- I've seen some clips.
- We don't see all the films.
- No, of course. There are so many.
Of course I do. Thank you.
Do you go for both the Bodil and
Robert Awards when you choose a part?
No. I go for
the Bodil Award, primarily.
- How believable was that line?
- Not bad.
The Robert Awards are a bit
more unpredictable, to be honest.
They're harder to plan for.
It seems very random.
You can look at something
and say, "This is Bodil material"?
Yes.
Didn't you feel
like an outsider sometimes?
Yes. I can't be so narcissistic,
stare at myself in the mirror
and do my hair for hours
like Peter Gantzler did.
But I've had other experiences
that they haven't had
because they were up in some loft,
doing improvisations.
The rest of us were out there
doing stand-up and making big money.
We're talking free drinks,
full throttle,
chicks and the rest of it.
That's what makes a man.
You can't ask more of a man than
what he can give. In that way...
I felt sorry for Jens.
He clearly wasn't up to the job.
And it's true that I taunted him
sometimes. Put him in his place.
Would you feel better if we didn't
talk about Peter Gantzler at all?
- That's probably the best thing.
- Jens, this movie...
No, stop it.
I can't do it anymore.
Trier's movies are very arty-farty,
I guess.
But Trier is an extremely
insecure man.
When he meets someone like me
who isn't, he attaches himself to me.
He calls me and says,
"What do I do? I don't want to fly."
I tell him,
"Goddamn it, Trier. Drive!"
You don't get that look from the
others, "She's won a lot of awards"?
- You'll have to ask them.
- You don't feel it?
I think I choose to shut it out.
Hasn't Trier won more awards
than me? He must have.
I wouldn't say I'm his mentor
or coach. I'm more a kind of rock
on which he can place
his film genius, perhaps.
- You bring Trier into a new era?
- No, he does that himself.
But we all know that if Iron Maiden
play a concert in Edinburgh...
they do the performing,
but how did they get there?
With your enormous
mental resources...
- I think it's safe to say that?
- Yes.
The resources that you have,
in this situation as well...
Right now? Yes.
If you were to draw on that to give
Lars von Trier some advice
to take with him
on his journey,
what would it be?
"When you can't be like me, Lars,
just be yourself."
Yes.
What's been
your best advice to him?
It must have been...
"Deep breaths, Lars.
Just get going.
Forget about doing
new things all the time.
Drop it. Let's have some fun."
When people look back at my films
in a hundred years' time,
they'll probably say, "Bloody hell!
That guy knew what he was doing."
I'll just go and check
that Iben is okay.
She's got the car keys, so...
- Don't you have any more questions?
- Yes.
We're just acting, aren't we?
- Are you acting?
- Yes. Couldn't you tell?
- No.
- Great acting. I really tried.
You've experienced it for yourself.
The insight into the world of art.
Powerlessness, power.
Joy, enthusiasm, feelings... fear.
Reality, parallel reality...
Thank you for watching.
When you turn up in the morning,
ready to shoot some scene...
it's like entering...
- different rooms.
- What rooms?
And one of those rooms
that you're constantly in
is the room filled with fear,
I guess.
If you don't want to do
the interview that we agreed on,
you can say whatever
you want. I'm leaving!
That's okay.
You can't help laughing
when you're fearful.
That's perfect. Brilliant.
Cut!
Why does he ask me that?
There was a bit more nonsense
in this one.
- I'm so involved with my work.
- That's good.
- "Pip."
He's fabulous.
Let me just have a look.
- And this one is all of the text?
- Yes, it's those two.
I'll get these onto some cardboard.
"And even though I may seem
like a reflection, this film is not."
I'm happy with it.
That's a punch right in their faces.
Put it there,
and I'll go up and have a look.
Put one here by my finger.
- That's nothing.
- There you go.
I'd like a movement going
diagonally across the windows.
This is some toy.
If this looks odd already, please stay,
because it won't be difficult.
- That's good.
- It's super! That's it.
- 13 degrees to the left.
- That won't work.
- It's the wrong direction.
- Let's have a new one.
Tilt down 11 degrees.
And 33 centimeters to the left.
You'll like this, Lars.
Well, if you're happy, I'm happy.